Hey everybody, it's Joshua Zabel, the
statistical CFO back with another
YouTube premiere.
If you like these YouTube premier, uh,
you can see on my shirt, I'm wearing a Mintab
exchange shirt.
Minitab exchanges are in-person events
where people a lot smarter than me come to
discuss different challenges and
organizations and explain how to problem
solve. So I encourage you to visit your Local
one, but for now, let's
stick to the agenda. So I'm
going to jump into my presentation. The presentation
today is about Monte Carlo simulation
and what a useful tool it is
for CFOs or other
finance professionals that are
usually forecasting.
All right.
Let's get into
the topic for today,
which is helping CFO's forecast
and provide confident guidance ranges
using Monte Carlo simulation. I
always like to start a little bit about
me, the statistical CFO, uh,
and about who this is for. It's really.
Members of the finance organizations
or frankly sales organizations, people
that might provide forecasts or guidance
ranges,
whether it be to your CFO,
to your CEO,
to the executive team, or to investors in
the case of a public or
private company setting.
More about me, I've got a
BA, an MA in economics, so I'm not
a statistician.
I am the current CFO. I've worked at
large companies, small companies,
private, public,
um, and on Wall Street, off Wall
Street, and
what really excites me about this discussion about Monte
Carlo is,
it's a great tool to communicate
what you're finding and what you're thinking.
Uh, and it really helps you as a
CFO or a professional,
uh, really lean into
information and data rather than gut
feel and instinct and bias,
and I'll show you how that comes
about. OK, so what is
Monte Carlo simulation?
Well, Monte Carlo simulation, you can
see a lot of these definitions. What
you're doing is assigning probability distributions
to uncertain inputs.
You're then using the computer to randomly
sample those distributions,
get some outcomes, and then analyze those
results. In layman's
terms, what it really means is when you have
a formula,
and if you kind of think of sales, let's
imagine you have sales that's comprised
of Division A, Division B, and Division
C, and there are all sorts of ranges of
those sales.
Rather than running through scenarios yourself,
Monte Carlo simulation runs those scenarios
for you
and actually gives you the percentages
or the risks of those outcomes.
So it really quantifies risks
or really scenario analysis.
I always think it's interesting to talk
about where these names came from.
Monte Carlo simulation actually was invented
as part of the Manhattan Project.
The scientists there were actually using this
approach, random sampling,
to solve their problems.
And they viewed it as similar to
gambling, which is where the Monte Carlo
casino comes in, the name,
and so that's how the name came
about, hence Monte Carlo.
OK, so why as a CFO
should you use it, or frankly as someone who's forecasting,
it allows you to plan using odds
and math, not just your opinion.
Thinking about there's a 24%
chance we're going to do this as opposed to I think
or I hope,
it incorporates analytics.
A lot of times forecasts are based
on instinct.
You're trying to read the people who are giving you the
forecast.
Some salespeople are biased
to be more conservative. Some are biased to be more.
Aggressive.
Uh, same thing with your marketing people might
consistently overspend or underspend.
Those are things in the mind of a CFO
that we try to do some math around.
Uh, this allows you to take analytics, uh,
which allows you to explain it and defend it.
It also helps you face realities.
Uh, I'd like to think people are inherently optimistic,
so we're hopeful that people will do better.
This puts some sobriety into
those forecasts,
and I think most importantly, it's a better
communication tool to your CEO
or your board.
It provides mathematical context
around that
forecast,
um, and it makes you sound smart, like you know what you're doing,
which is always a bonus too.
So, how simple can it be? It actually
can be quite simple. Uh, Monte Carlo simulation
sounds really fancy and may be advanced,
um, and frankly speaking, the more complex your
equation is,
the more useful it is.
Uh, so it can be quite complex, but it also
can be quite simple and used in a really simple
way. And I'm going to show you
examples
that are really simple, that are applicable
to things that you probably see all the time,
uh, and you'll see how easy it can be.
So let's start with that simple
example.
You're a CFO. I'm a CFO
trying to project revenues for a quarter.
Hypothetically, maybe you have 3 regions.
You can see the regions are projecting
different levels.
In this case, I have $10.20
dollars, $17 for each region
for the quarter.
But what they do typically in a forecast
is they'll highlight.
Various things at risk and they'll also
highlight potential upside.
So what do you do with this as a CFO
or a sales leader
or an executive who gets these
type of forecasts?
So you can see the basic math is if
you take the forecast,
uh, you have a forecast of $47
pretty straightforward.
If you look at the downside risk, you're
looking at $34
and if you look at the upside, it's $61.
And so now you have a situation where
you have a range of 34 to 61,
uh, with a forecast of 47.
Um, and that's all fine and good
until you start getting questions about this
from your boss or your board.
Um, and using Monte Carlo will give
us some of those contextual
answers.
So let me go specifically. So
this forecast gets presented,
the range is 34 to 61, and the
forecast is 47.
And so a board might actually ask you something
like, how likely is it we hit 34,
because that's really bad,
um, or a more optimistic board might
say, how likely is it we hit 64, that'd
be great.
Um, what do you think?
In your judgment, you know, what do you
think? Um,
The CEO may say, OK,
understanding those things, how much should we spend?
Because if 34 is a reality,
then we better cut back on spending
because we don't want to spend more money than our revenues.
But on the flip side, if 61
is a reality,
we should be investing some
of that upside.
So what should we do, Mr. CFO
or Mrs. CFO?
And then in the context of a public company,
imagine you get this and you're asked to give a guidance
range of revenue forecasts.
How do you give that range, 34
to 64,
is a pretty large range.
So what I'm going to ask you to do is take a moment now,
think about what you would do,
and I would say take a screenshot of
this slide,
because as I go through the exercise here, I'm
going to allude to these numbers,
and, and I just want you to kind of think context
of how you would deal with it.
So I'm actually going to jump into the software in a
minute. Uh, but before I
jump into the software, when
you use Monte Carlo simulation,
you use different distributions
to do the simulation.
In statistics, distribution just describes
how a variables value
or spread out arranged possible
outcomes.
Uh, showing which values are more frequent or which
are less.
There are various distributions
that could be a whole talk in and of itself,
which I'm not going to jump into,
but I'm going to highlight three distributions
that I think are particularly applicable
for people in finance, or at least
the way we think.
The first one is a normal distribution. The
normal distribution is the classic bell
curve distribution, where most data
points cluster around the mean.
We all know that.
Then there's a triangular distribution. The reason
why I like it for financial
situations is oftentimes in finance,
we think of things in 3 cases.
We think of a bear case,
the minimum, a bull case, which
is the maximum, and a base case, which is
the most likely.
And so that's a helpful context to
think about how you could use Monte Carlo.
The other thing is a uniform distribution.
Which really deals with if you have a range.
So in the case that you just have the bear case
and the bull case, or the best case and the worst case,
it's a helpful range.
Now, I'm going to jump into the software
and show you how easy it is to do.
So I'm going to pull over
my web browser.
I'm gonna jump right into
app.minitab,
which is the mini tab Solution Center.
I'm gonna jump right into.
Minitab workspace, one of the applications
in the Solution Center,
which has our Monte Carlo simulation.
And when you get here, you can see it's asking
for a model and outputs.
And
if you remember, what did we talk about? We talked
about we wanted to, we had 3 regions, so
I'm going to say region 1.
Region 2
And
region 3.
I'm going to use the uniform distribution
for all of them.
That was the one that just had the, the range,
the worst and the, and the best, and I asked
you to take a screenshot of this,
and you can see we started with
9 to 12,
and then we had 15
to 22
and
to 27.
And then all I'm going to do is say total sales.
And you can see here the equation
is of total sales is my 3 regions
added up, which is region 1 plus region
2 plus region 3.
And I'm gonna hit enter.
I have my
equation in, and now I'm gonna
do a simulation run,
and so that's it. It's simple as that.
I'm done.
You can see here the mean is 47,
uh, which is, which is good
because it actually shows that's pretty close to my
forecast.
Um, and then you can see other percentiles,
which I'm gonna dive into later.
Uh, but I'm going to first, what I like to
do is run the simulation multiple
times,
uh, with different,
uh, distributions. So I'm going to duplicate this distribution.
I now have it all over again. You can see it's
again, but this time instead of uniform,
I'm going to do triangular.
Remember, triangular was the base case.
The bull case and the bear case,
and if you'll remember here for
the regions I had 9 with a
forecast of 10 as the base case
and the bull case of 12
for the lower on the next one, I
had 15 as the bear case with
20 as the base and 22
as the bowl case.
And for the last region,
I have 10.
17 and 27.
And again, the same equation, I'm
just gonna run the simulation again.
There we go.
And you can see results again. Interestingly
enough, I have the mean of 47, so that's
great, and percentiles, which again, I'm
gonna show you in a minute.
Um, and then last, I'm gonna copy
this again.
And I'm going to run the normal distribution,
which I talked about.
Now, the difference in the normal distribution is
you can see, you have your mean,
uh, which in this case is going to be
10.
20 and 17
and standard deviation,
the quick
way to calculate standard deviation is take
the range over 4.
I've done that math,
uh, in preparing,
uh, but if you look at the slide I asked
you to take a screenshot of, you can quickly
take the ranges all of the, the,
the top of the range minus the bottom of the range,
divide by 4.
In this one, it was 10 was the range, divided by
4 is 2.5.
Um, and once again, I'm going to run the simulation.
And again, I got a mean of 47.
So, really good news. I got 3 means
of 47. My forecast is 47,
so I'm feeling pretty good. Now, what I'm going to do is
go switch back now
to
the, uh, I'm going to take this
and move it away for now,
and I'm going to switch back to
my presentation mode here,
and I'm going to show you the results
of those simulations.
So here are the results of the simulations.
Um, like I said, you can run one
type of stimulation. I like to run multiple
ones just because you see how quick and easy
it is,
and it gives you more context and more
confidence.
The way to read these, when you look at these percentiles,
and you can see I have it written down,
we'll start with the first uniform distribution, is
90%
of the simulated outcomes are going to be less
than or equal to 55,
in this case, or 54.67.
The second. Uh, analysis or
stimulation came up with 52.5,
and the third one was 52.9.
Uh, so
that goes when we go into the ranges
that we talked about, the upside of
61.
This gives me a pretty good impression
that 61 probably isn't a realistic
outcome.
How good can it be if the board asks?
Somewhere between 53
and 55 is probably a good
answer. Maybe you guessed 54
as a good range.
And then the other part is how bad can it be?
Uh, and again, looking at that 10th
percentile, so there's less than 10%
chance
the value is, uh,
in this case in a uniform 40,
the 2nd 142, and the 3rd 141,
and I'll highlight that here. Here's your 40, 42,
and 41.
Again,
when we looked at the first situation, our
worst case scenario was 34.
So when the board asked me how I feel about
this forecast,
the nice thing was we saw the
mean of 47 come up a
few times,
so I feel pretty good about that forecast of
47 as the best
guess I can make.
Um, but I would also say that the range
is more realistic, something like,
you know, 41 or 40
to 42
to something like 54,
right? Which is a much tighter range
than the 34 to 61.
OK, so that's pretty simple.
Um, let's up the ante
here and make it a little more complex,
because you may say, well, that really seems simple. I don't really
need to do that,
um. OK, so now let's use those
same regions, those same
revenue projections here with
the same uncertainty around them, but
now we're trying to forecast the
operating income or the EBIT.
And so
we get a forecast from our sales team,
but our chief marketing officer says,
uh, and our CRO says, well,
our expenses are expected to be in the range of 10 to
15. We're not quite sure.
Um, and then our R&D and development team
says, well, the expenses are in a range of 6 to
10. So now I've
added another
layer of complexity
because if I look at my forecasting
math of 47,
I had that downside of 34 to 61.
And now if the board says to you, what's the best
case scenario,
the best case scenario would be the 61, which
is the best case revenue, and the
least amount of expense, which would be 10
and 6, which would get me an operating
income of 45.
The worst case scenario would be the worst revenue
case and the most expenses, which would
be 9.
So now I've got a situation where I've got a range of
45 and 9 or 9 to
45,
which is a huge range. I have the
board asking me what I think
is likely going to happen.
Um, and right now the way I'm
doing that is guessing it. I'm basically
saying, well,
my marketing person is traditionally
conservative, so she's probably
OK at $10.
My R&D folks are traditionally
aggressive,
so, you know, they are saying $6 to $10
but really, They're going to spend 12, I don't know.
And so
the way you want to give an answer is preferably
with the data. What is the data telling you?
Because that allows you to look at your board or your
CEO or your investors and say,
hey, look, based on the information I
have, this is the best guess I
can make based on the data.
So
how are we going to do this?
So I'm going to stick to a uniform distribution
because it's right now we believe
all the data points are
likely. We don't have any belief about
that distribution,
and so I'm going to jump in the software
again. So
let's hold on one second as I jump in
the software.
I'm dragging the software over
again. I'm going to go to my nice navigator.
I'm going to go to my first simulation,
which had the uniform distribution,
as you'll see. So if we look at the model,
you'll remember I had the uniform distribution.
I'm going to duplicate this simulation,
and I'm going to add.
Another X and another Y, and
the first X is gonna be sales
and marketing expense.
And
3, I'll just say R&D
for the interest.
Um, and again, we're gonna say that uniform
distribution, which is the one that you have the low
case and the best case,
and if you remember here,
my sales and marketing was gonna be 10
to 15.
And my R&D was going to be 6 to 10.
But my equation has to change here, so
if you remember.
To find my operating income.
I'm gonna take my sales, only
this time I'm actually gonna subtract out
my expenses.
So,
not a very
complicated
equation here, but more complicated
than just the addition,
and I'm going to quickly run a simulation.
And again, here you can see the mean of 27,
that's important.
I'm going to go back to my
presentation where I've
highlighted the
Answers to make it much easier.
And so
again, looking at that distribution here
you can see at the 90th percentile
we're at 34.5
and the 10% is
19.
And so
rather than telling the board or my CEO I
have a range of 9. To 45.
Um, I can tighten that range
much more, 19 to 35,
and with a mean of 27,
gives me a really good data-driven
analysis
of what I believe the forecast
range is and the likely outcomes
will be.
So, let's review. First
of all,
uh, you can now talk about Monte Carlo
at cocktail parties and at your board,
which will make you sound smart,
hopefully.
Uh, but more importantly,
uh, keep in mind, Monte Carlo
provides insight. It lets you see a range of possibilities
and their likelihood,
and really lets you quantify risk.
It can be used for simple analysis, as I showed
you, or more complex.
Uh, the more complex your equation,
as you saw, the more utility it
has because by definition, there's more variability,
so it's really helpful.
Um, and I think where it's really
critical is a communication
tool. Um,
again, the CFO is always looked
to as what is your belief
of these things are going to happen and
inherently we have judgment, and
CFO does have some judgment and uses
judgment.
Uh, but a better CFO incorporates
data-driven analysis
with that judgment,
um, and Monte Carlo is a great way
to provide that data-driven analysis.
So, that's the end of our talk.
Uh, if you have any questions, uh,
please submit them, uh, and, and
hopefully you have been submitting them, and we'll
get back to you.
And please comment if there's any other topics
on simulation or statistics that
you want to learn.
Thank you very much and have a great
day. Bye.